A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Welfare Interests - Youth, Series R FA327
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - Contributions to War Funds, 1917-1918 (Box 22, Folder 218)
    John D. Rockefeller,Jr. contributions to Young Men's Christian Association $35,000,000 Fund, to National War Work Council. List of Standard Oil, Rockefeller Foundation, Abeyton Realty Company, and Colorado Fuel & Iron Company contributions to Young Men's Christian Association and Red Cross war work.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Trip Abroad, 1919 (Box 22, Folder 219)
    Abandonment of plans for trip; Knights of Columbus work in France. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John R. Mott, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Work Council - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Trip Abroad - Passport, 1919 (Box 22, Folder 220)
    Resolution that John D. Rockefeller, Jr. be requested to go overseas; letter from Acting Secretary of State Frank Polk, introducing John D. Rockefeller, Jr.; application for Italian and French visas; list of committee members.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Prisoners' Aid, 1939-1947 (Box 22, Folder 221)
    Sending of book, "I Was in Prison"; copy of book in file. Data on prisoner of war camps and Young Men's Christian Association wartime ministry to prisoners. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to International Committee to work with prisoners of war; contributions by Sealantic Fund and Rockefeller Brothers Fund. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Willard S. Richardson, Arthur W. Packard, John R. Mott, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - War Prisoners' Aid - "I Was In Prison" (Box 22, Folder 222)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Army and Navy, 1940-1941 (Box 22, Folder 223)
    Expansion of Young Men's Christian Association facilities required due to rapid growth of military services; survey of needs. John D. Rockefeller 3rd declined to become member of Young Men's Christian Association Army and Navy Committee. Appeals to Rockefellers to help out various Y's serving military personnel declined. Suggested nondenomination prayers supplied to Young Men's Christian Association by United Service Organizations (USO) via John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Lyman Pierce, Frederick Osborn, Norris Tibbets, Paul Debevoise.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Army and Navy, 1942-1961 (Box 22, Folder 224)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Army and Navy - National Recreation Association Underwriting, 1940-1941 (Box 22, Folder 225)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. loaned Association $4,000 for its work with army camps; repayment of loan.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee, 1900-1912 (Box 22, Folder 226)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledges for Endowment Fund, expenses of Dr. Johnson's trip, Mott's salary and tour of Orient and Balkans; good reports on tours. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to World's Conference Committee at Paris; letter introducing Roger Greene. Summary of pledges by Rockefeller Foundation and Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledges, 1892-1912. Mr. Murray's report on the Orient; 50-year celebration; Lyman Hoover views regarding future of Young Men's Christian Association in Communist China. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Richard Moise, G. F. Peabody, Starr J. Murphy, Howard A. Johnson, John R. Mott, John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Frederick T. Gates, William D. Murray, Willard S. Richardson, Lyman Hoover, C. J. Hicks.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee, 1911-1942 (Box 22, Folder 227)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee, 1943-1961 (Box 22, Folder 228)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - February 9, 1906 Pledge, 1906-1908 (Box 23, Folder 229)
    Pledge for erection of buildings in Latin America and Philippines; American influence in Latin America.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - John R. Mott Regarding Pledges, 1900-1917 (Box 23, Folder 230)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - 1904 Student Work Pledges, 1904-1912 (Box 23, Folder 231)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge for continuance of Bible study among students; pledges to Washington evangelical Campaign and Mr. Cooper's Bible study course.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Address at Cleveland Convention, 1916 (Box 23, Folder 232)
    Plans for John D. Rockefeller, Jr. speech; preparation of printed copies; no copy of address in file.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Statement Regarding Gifts, 1922-1926 (Box 23, Folder 233)
    Summary of gifts by John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, Rockefeller Foundation, to Young Men's Christian Association and YMCA work.
    See also Box 46, Folder 523.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Army and Navy, 1898-1915 (Box 23, Folder 234)
    Work of Young Men's Christian Association Navy Department; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledge for erection of building at Norfolk; letter for cornerstone by John D. Rockefeller, Sr.; inscription for tablet. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Contributions, 1940-1949 (Box 23, Folder 235)
    Contributions by Abby Rockefeller Mauz, Jay Urice, Cleveland Dodge, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Dana S. Creel.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Contributions - Buildings for Brotherhood, 1957-1961 (Box 23, Folder 236)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $500,000 to project for rehabilitation and construction of Young Men's Christian Association buildings overseas; printed material; progress reports.
    See also Box 47, Folder 542.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Centennial Fund, 1944-1946 (Box 23, Folder 237)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $295,000; use of his pledge letter in proposed appeal to businessmen; Chinese gift to Fund. Campaign succeeded in its aim - to liquidate International Committee's accumulated deficit. Correspondents include Spencer Robertson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Centennial Fund - October 6, 1944 Pledge, 1944-1945 (Box 23, Folder 238)
    Conditional pledge of 5,000 shares of Standard Oil of New Jersey stock; question of when conditions would be satisfied.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Foreign Work, 1901-1913 (Box 23, Folder 239)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledges, 1901-1906, for erection of Young Men's Christian Association buildings and homes for secretaries overseas; and for work of Foreign Department; 1911-1918 pledges; contributions through Rockefeller Foundation; payment of Dr. Fosdick's trip to the Orient, 1921. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gifts to budget. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, John R. Mott, Richard C. Moise.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Foreign Work, 1914-1924 (Box 23, Folder 240)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Home Work, 1897-1911 (Box 24, Folder 241)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledges for Home Department activities; Young Men's Christian Association work among troops, Bible Study, Dr. Mott's work; payment of Dr. Mott's salary; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. subscriptions through Rockefeller Foundation; designation of special sum for work in Colorado. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, John R. Mott, Willis E. Lougee, R. C. Moise.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Home Work, 1912-1924 (Box 24, Folder 242)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - John R. Mott, 1914-1928 (Box 24, Folder 243)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledge to finance Mott's trip to the Near East; trip cancelled because of war; work among prisoners of war; hopes for a Christian Russia. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., J. R. Mott, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - John R. Mott - Young Men's Christian Association Retirement Fund, 1921-1926 (Box 24, Folder 244)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to plan, August 11, 1921; subscription by Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - John R. Mott - Contributions (Box 24, Folder 245)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - John R. Mott - Gift to Conference, 1931 (Box 24, Folder 246)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $10,000 through Dr. Mott to cover costs of Conference of World Alliance of YMCA's.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - John R. Mott - International Committee Report, 1923 (Box 24, Folder 247)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Sex Lectures, 1914-1917 (Box 24, Folder 248)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge for salaries and expenses of sex education lecturers; Dr. Winfield Hall's lectures; Moran's reports of activities and proposed curriculum of Social Hygiene Institute, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. comments; Moran's relief work with prisoners of war in Russia. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Charles Hurrey, Hugh A. Moran, Dr. W. Hall.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Sex Lectures - Pledge, 1913-1914 (Box 24, Folder 249)
    Suggested program of sex education among school boys; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to pay Dr. Moran's salary and expenses; pledge to Department of Sex Hygiene of International Committee.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Sex Lectures - Dr. Exner, 1915-1920 (Box 24, Folder 250)
    Program and policy for sex education in colleges and universities; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. personal donations to Dr. Exner; work of Dr. Exner's office.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Starr J. Murphy Report - Parts I and II, 1904 (Box 25, Folder 251)
    Study of Young Men's Christian Association Movement.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Starr J. Murphy Report - Parts III, IV, and V, 1904 (Box 25, Folder 252)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - June 14, 1910 Pledge, 1910-1917 (Box 25, Folder 253)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $540,000 to Foreign Department of International Committee. Correspondents include John R. Mott, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - March 30, 1917 Pledge, 1916-1922 (Box 25, Folder 254)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr.'s conditional $1,000,000 pledge cancelled. Needs of Foreign Association Building Program. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Starr J. Murphy, John R. Mott.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association, 1904-1958 (Box 25, Folder 255)
    Purchase of Silver Bay, hotel for use in Young Men's Christian Association Summer Conference and training of leaders. Pledges from John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Formation of Silver Bay Association. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Starr J. Murphy, Arthur W. Packard, C. J. Hicks, Dana S. Creel, R. C. Moise.
    See also Box 47, Folder 541.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association - Eastern Association School, 1914-1929 (Box 25, Folder 256)
    Work of School; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution to deficit.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association - Silver Bay School for Boys, 1916-1919 (Box 25, Folder 257)
    Plans for purchase of building for use as library and administration building; named Richard C. Moise Hall; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association - June 30, 1931 Pledge to Silver Bay Institute (Box 25, Folder 258)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to Institute.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association - March 1, 1932 Pledge (Box 25, Folder 259)
    Continuation of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s 1931 pledge.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Silver Bay Association - Contributions, 1952-1958 (Box 25, Folder 260)
    Nonrecurring 1952 contribution to 50th Anniversary fund by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 1958 contribution to help purchase property.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Survey of Educational Activities, 1923 (Box 25, Folder 261)
    Printed report.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - United States Public Health Service, 1919-1922 (Box 25, Folder 262)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to physical fitness campaign; renewal of pledge.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Incorporation, 1917 (Box 25, Folder 263)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students, 1916-1924 (Box 25, Folder 264)
    Work among foreign, particularly Oriental, students in the United States, closely related to Young Men's Christian Association Foreign Department. Studies on students' needs; formation of Emergency Relief Committee for Foreign Students. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller gifts.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students, 1929-1954 (Box 26, Folder 265)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - International Committee - Committee on Friendly Relations Among Foreign Students - May 1932 Appeal, 1931-1932 (Box 26, Folder 266)
    Reports on Oriental Student Christian Conferences, 1931-1932; list of large contributors. Declination of appeal.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - World Youth Fund, 1944-1957 (Box 26, Folder 267)
    Seeking to "bring Christian democratic influences" to "youth of war-ravaged countries." John D. Rockefeller, Jr. was member of Fund's National Advisory Council, made contribution, declined later appeals for participation and contributions. Laurance S. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. declined to act as sponsors. Correspondents include W. Spencer Robertson, Arthur W. Packard, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Cleveland Dodge, Laurance S. Rockefeller.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - World Youth Fund - Contributions, 1946-1947 (Box 26, Folder 268)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave over $250,000.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council, 1925-1947 (Box 26, Folder 269)
    Reports of activities; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. centennial message; plans for writing a Young Men's Christian Association history. Japanese Young Men's Christian Association/Hostels project; lists of contributors. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Raymond B. Fosdick, Thomas B. Appleget, Willard S. Richardson, Dana S. Creel, Eugene Barnett, Arthur W. Packard.
    See also Box 46, Folder 524, 525.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council, 1948-1953 (Box 26, Folder 270)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council, 1950-1950 (Box 26, Folder 271)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council, 1953-1959 (Box 26, Folder 272)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Contributions, 1925-1930 (Box 26, Folder 273)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 1925 $100,000 special contribution, with provision that deficit financing policy would be abandoned. Formation of new National Council; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. large annual contributions to it, 1925-1930. No material for 1930-1950. 1950-1959, $5,000 annual contributions; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. 1955 gift to World Alliance of Young Men's Christian Associations. Letters of appeal include long reports on Young Men's Christian Association work in America and abroad. Correspondents include John R. Mott, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget, Jay Urice.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Contributions, 1950-1955 (Box 26, Folder 274)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Contributions, 1955-1959 (Box 26, Folder 275)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Contributions - June 1, 1928 Pledge, $100,000, 1928-1929 (Box 27, Folder 276)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Contributions - April 26, 1929 Pledge, $100,000, 1929-1930 (Box 27, Folder 277)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Contributions - John R. Mott Fellowship Fund, 1956 (Box 27, Folder 278)
    Fund is part of National Young Men's Christian Association Scholarship Program; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gave $540,000 for Program and Fund, for training future Young Men's Christian Association secretaries.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Building Program, July 12, 1922 Pledge, 1922-1930 (Box 27, Folder 279)
    Cancellation of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. Pledge, replaced by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge; amendments. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt, John R. Mott, Willard S. Richardson, A. L. Boulware.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Building Program, July 12, 1922 Pledge - Jerusalem Young Men's Christian Association, 1923-1933 (Box 27, Folder 280)
    Plans for erecting building; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. made honorary life member; dedication of building.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Colored Work, 1931-1944 (Box 27, Folder 281)
    Summary of Young Men's Christian Association work with Negroes; work of Colored Work Division. Channing Tobias's memories of John D. Rockefeller, Sr. Correspondents include Channing H. Tobias, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - Colored Work - Contributions, 1931-1934 (Box 27, Folder 282)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledges to Home Missionary Fund, Colored Work Department.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - July 1932 Appeal, 1932-1933 (Box 27, Folder 283)
    Appeal for National and International Council; treasurer's report. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Francis S. Harmon.
    See also Box 46, Folder 526.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - December 28, 1928 Pledge, 1928-1930 (Box 27, Folder 284)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to stabilization fund. Correspondents include John R. Mott, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas B. Appleget.
    See also Box 47, Folder 540.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Council - March 20, 1930 Pledge, 1929-1930 (Box 27, Folder 285)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. pledge to budget. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Max Yergen Work in Africa, 1927-1947 (Box 27, Folder 286)
    Work in the Union of South Africa; John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to building for training of Negro leaders. Correspondents include Max Yergan, Thomas B. Appleget, John R. Mott, George F. Peabody.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Student Council, 1938-1960 (Box 27, Folder 287)
    Rejuvenation of Student Christian Movement, affiliated with Young Men's Christian Association as National Student Council of the YMCA. Criticisms of organization; projects. Laurance S. Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller 3rd contributions. Correspondents include Pitney Van Dusen, Edwin Espy, Rev. L. Tucker, Laurance S. Rockefeller, Arthur W. Packard, Edgar B. Young, Dana S. Creel, Yorke Allen.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Student Council - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1936-1949 (Box 28, Folder 288)
    Contributions began as a result of friendship with Luther Tucker and were for Negro and interracial work of the Student Christian Movement. Organization charts, reports on work, contributions 1937-1951.
    See also Box 46, Folder 527.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Student Council - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1950-1953 (Box 28, Folder 289)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - National Student Council - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1955-1956 (Box 28, Folder 0289A)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - California - San Francisco, 1906-1935 (Box 28, Folder 290)
    Loss of Young Men's Christian Association building in earthquake; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledge to replace building. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, Cleveland Dodge, Henry McCloy.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Colorado - Estes Park Conference - Denver, 1910-1933 (Box 28, Folder 291)
    Activities of Young Men's Christian Association Western Conference; needs for place for training of workers. Pledges by John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Washington, D.C., 1903-1912 (Box 28, Folder 292)
    Needs of Negro Young Men's Christian Association in Washington; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. conditional pledge. Senator Aldrich's letter introducing Henry MacFarland, President of the District of Columbia Board of Commissioners. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, H. B. MacFarland, Nelson W. Aldrich.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Florida - Daytona Beach, 1922-1944 (Box 28, Folder 293)
    John D. Rockefeller, Sr. contributions to Volusia County and Halifax Young Men's Christian Association, and to building fund. John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contribution. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Georgia - Atlanta - Georgia School of Technology, 1909-1933 (Box 28, Folder 294)
    Book of remembrance containing letters of appreciation for 1910 gift to building fund. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John R. Mott.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Georgia - Atlanta - Georgia School of Technology, 1932 (Box 28, Folder 295)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Illinois - Chicago - George Williams College, 1929-1945 (Box 28, Folder 296)
    Needs of Young Men's Christian Association College; reorganization; John D. Rockefeller, Sr. pledge; June 8, 1933 amendment. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, Thomas B. Appleget.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Illinois - Chicago - George Williams College - April 4, 1930 Pledge and Payment, 1930-1934 (Box 28, Folder 297)
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Maine - Hancock County, 1913-1925 (Box 28, Folder 298)
    See also Box 46, Folder 528.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Maine - Bar Harbor, 1908-1932 (Box 29, Folder 299)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr. contributions to Bar Harbor Young Men's Christian Association; summary of contributions to Seal Harbor activities. Renewal of annual contributions; underwriting of expenses of survey. 1930, $5,000 contribution to special capital funds program. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Arthur W. Packard, Charles O. Heydt, Samuel J. Robbins, David Rockefeller.
  - Young Men's Christian Association - Maine - Bar Harbor, 1933-1949 (Box 29, Folder 300)
    See also Box 47, Folder 543.